Guide to the Faculty papers and memorabilia, 1823-2001 MS2132.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Personal papers, 1823-1990; MS2132 Series 2; 6 Linear feet (Box 8, Box 15, Box 11, Box 9, Box 13, Box 10, Box 12, Box 3, Box 5, Box 7, Box 14, Box 6, Box 4)
  - Diaries, 1898 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Materials in this collection include photocopies of diaries that McNeil kept. In the early diarys, Hiram coded his entried. The following is the key to that code:
  - Diaries, 1899 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1901 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1902 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1903 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Diaries, 1904 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1905 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1907 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Diaries, 1908 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Diaries, 1910 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Diaries, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Diaries, 1912 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Diaries, 1913 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Diaries, 1914 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Diaries, 1915 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Diaries, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Diaries, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Diaries, 1918 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Diaries, 1919 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1920 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1921 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1922 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1923 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Diaries, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1925 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1926 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Diaries, 1928 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, 1929 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Diaries, 1930 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Diaries, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Diaries, 1932 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Diaries, 1933 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Diaries, 1934 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Diaries, 1935 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Diaries, 1936 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Diaries, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - G.W. Library articles, newsletters, etc., undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Dedication of Mason Room, 03/1974 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Exhibit of John Russell Mason: newsletters, invitation, program, speech, photograph
  - John R. Mason Book Fund - Gelman Library: correspondence, newsletter, 03/1974 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - GWU Library Council: correspondence, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Arts Club of Washington--Monroe House: speech, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    Includes photograph
  - John R. Mason's Retirement: news article, correspondence, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Christmas correspondence, biographical material, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of paintings in the Mason Room of the GW Library, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Photograph of Elmer Louis Kayser, 1920 ca. (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - John Russell Mason's death and memorial service, 1981 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - John Russell Mason's cremation, burial etc., 1981 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - John Russell Mason's Library Book Fund materials, 1981 ca. (Box 14, Folder 13)
    Estate inventory, First Codicil, Power of Attorney, Last Will
  - Photographs of John Russell Mason, 1940 ca. (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - William Carl Ruediger miscellaneous papers, 1935 (Box 16, Volume 1)
    William Carl Ruediger (1874-1947) was a Professor of Education at George Washington University from 1907-1939, and Dean of the School of Education from 1912-36. He was author of numerous works in the field of education, among the best known being "Principles of Education and Teaching Procedures." Titles of articles: Concerning Methods of Teaching the Language, 1902; Abstract Thought and the Moral Life, 1909; Extension Teaching, 1912; Teaching the Fundamentals, 1913; Realness in Teaching, 1915; Credit for Quality, 1915; Teaching Individual Notions, 1916; The After-Training of Teachers, 1917; The Spirit of the Teaching Corps, 1918; Unionism Among Teachers, 1918; Local Signature and Sensational Extensity, 1919; Basic Courses in Education, 1919; Professional Majority, 1921; Acquiring Habits of Correct Speech, 1921; Projects and the Project Method, 1921; Baiting Teachers, 1923; Mental Discipline, 1924; Homogeneous Grouping of Pupils, 1924; Monism and Consciousness, 1924; Rating Teachers, 1924; Evolution, 1926; New Duties New Occasions Teach, 1926; The Permanence of Educational Effects, 1927; The Christian College, 1927; Individual Differences, 1928; Education at the Crossroads, 1929; The Parent-Teacher Movement, 1929; the Teacher's Calling, 1929; English and the Ph. D., 1929; Educational Objectives, 1929; Causes of Small Families, 1931; Health Investment, 1931; Education and Eugenics, 1931; The Principles of Teaching, 1932; The Balance between Subject-matter and Method, 1932; The Learning Unit, 1932; English Secondary Education, 1933; Obstacles to Moral Advancement, 1934; Unity in the Teaching Profession, 1934; Federal Aid to Schools, 1935.
  - William Carl Ruediger Psychology, undated (Box 16, Volume 2)
    William Carl Ruediger (1874-1947) was a Professor of Education at George Washington University from 1907-1939, and Dean of the School of Education from 1912-36. He was author of numerous works in the field of education, among the best known being "Principles of Education and Teaching Procedures."
  - William Carl Ruediger Elementary Ethics, 1905 (Box 16, Volume 3)
  - Letter from faculty member Irah Chase to Rev. John Williams, 1822 October 22; Series 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    This letter is about the first year of the Columbian College. Chase was one of the original faculty members. Having just recovered from a "severe attack of fever," he tells Rev. Williams that "The college here prospers beyond the most sanguine expectations. The whole number of students already amounts to nearly fifty. The policy which I have deemed it a duty to pursue, has been to introduce as early as possible such habits of order and industry as shall not need to be changed and to endeavour by every means in our power, to make an education here as sound and as extensive as at any college in the Union." Chase goes on to explain about the school's public worship, notes establishment of a Sunday school and ends with a discussion of an upcoming "General Convention" and of having met a young man named Ludlow of New York. Chase went on to help found Andover Newton Theological School.
  - Correspondence addressed to Howard Lincoln Hodgkins, 1895-1904 (Box 17)
  - Oswald Symister Colclough correspondence and reports related to his work for the U.S. Navy, including as a delegate to the International Conference on the Law of the Sea, 1957-1960; 4 folder(s) (Box 17)